in this video i'm going to show you how
to browse the internet right from within
your terminal window using something
called w3m now w3m is a text based
browser web browser i should say and
it'll allow you to view web pages just
the html of web pages no javascript css
or pictures or anything like that just
the text that exists on a web page you
can see with the w3m browser and i'm
going to give you a brief overview of
that just to get you started up and
running with it so let's go ahead and
try that out this will work on
pretty much a lot of a lot of linux
systems i can't say all of them but i'm
using ubuntu here and what we want to do
is first install that package so that's
apt install
just like i said w3m
and already have it on my system so
there's nothing for me to do but go
ahead and get that
and then
let's go to our first web page it's
really easy w3m then the name of the
page that you want to go to so we will
go to good old google.com
now like i said this is just text okay
so you got your tabs at the top here
and i can't click anything i'm just
showing you with my mouse the search
form in the middle with the search
button and i'm feeling lucky button
advanced search and then the footer at
the bottom so to navigate you can either
use your arrow keys
or if you want to go to the next like i
forget what like the next highlightable
element you can use the tab key and
that'll take you directly to the search
box now to enter text you can hit the
enter key and then down here at the
bottom you'll see it says text that you
want to enter into that text box
i'm going to say what time is it
in
london
so i'll hit enter to apply that to the
text box then i'll use my tab key to go
to the next element which is the search
button right here and then to select
that button i can hit enter
that'll actually go do the google search
return the page and again it's a text
based page you got your little snippet
up here that says london uk local time 7
23 pm on friday november 19 2021 so if
you didn't notice
or if you didn't know this i record a
lot of my videos way ahead of time and
then publish them
on a schedule tuesdays thursdays
in the future so that's why that's
probably a lot different from what
you're seeing
right now
let's do another search let's
again i'm going to use either the arrow
keys or the tab key to get to the next
element
and then if i want to change it same
thing hit enter to select that box now
we can either backspace
or we can use the shortcut
ctrl u
to just clear that out
and then we'll search for tony teaches
teaches tech
hit enter
tab over to the search button hit enter
so there's a little bit of a learning
curve but once you get the hang of it
it's actually pretty handy to to
navigate through these pages
so here's all the search results we've
got my my website my youtube channel
another youtube channel link
um and if you you can use the arrow keys
again or you can use the page down to go
down to the next page
um so you got some some more stuff
tony teaches tech net worth in 2021
let's see what that's all about
so i went too far there tab tab went
down two tabs if you want to go back to
the previous one you can do shift tab
shift tab and then hit enter the one
you're interested in
so that should open up that page in just
a second
and whoops
i went too far so how do we go back to
go back
is simply
[Music]
shift b
and now we're on the previous page so
let's go explore this page i have 1.7
1.17 million views 12 000 subs
this seems a little bit a little bit out
of date
um
the net worth of tony teaches tech's
channel through november
19th 2021 is 7534.
that is not accurate maybe we'll save
what that actual value is
for another video
but let's continue on with this tutorial
so let's go to
um let's go to a specific url
and we can do that by typing shift u
and you'll see that shows up the current
url we can clear that out again with
control u
and let's go to
wordpress.org
wordpress.org okay go ahead type that in
hit enter
and this is
wordpress.org's website so say we want
to find something specific on this web
page
uh you can do that if you're familiar
with vim
you can do that with just typing slash
and i'm going to look for i see it right
there but i'm going to look for the
percent sign
hit enter
and there you go it finds that percent
so 42 percent of the web uses wordpress
which is a really cool
fact
that's that's crazy almost half the the
web uses wordpress
you can also use multiple tabs in this
web browser so in order to open up a new
tab
do shift t
and now you'll see that
pretty much copies
the tab that we were on so this right
here is the the first tab and this right
here is the second tab so
in the second tab
let's go to something new let's go to
let's use control u
i'm sorry shift u capital u to go to a
specific url let's go to
duck
go
now you can see clearly that we have two
tabs open and if we want to ship switch
between the two tabs we can do shift
open bracket to go to this tab right
here
to the left and shift close bracket to
go to the tab on the right so let's
let's do a quick uh search
on duckduckgo so we'll tab down in there
hit enter
type in like comment
subscribe
hit enter to apply that text i typed
lick comment subscribe
uh we'll do the search anyway hit enter
and now
uh
we are on the search results here let's
say we want to go back
to the previous page because we we
realized that we misspelled it so or you
know we actually have the option of
changing here but let's to show you how
to go back you can go back a page with
shift b
okay and that'll go back to the previous
page
um if we wanted to get out of duckduck
or if we want to go out of w3m
altogether
simply type q
and it says do you want to exit w3m yes
or no i'm going to type y and that takes
you back to your terminal window
let's go back through it'll it'll have a
fresh session for you no tabs or
anything like that
but you can still see your search
history uh by typing in control h
and that'll show all the
the the websites that we have been to
and if you need help in general with the
w3m text based browser
from any page you can just type capital
h
and that'll go through all of the
navigation commands that you need to
know about but hopefully the ones that i
gave you in this video are helpful to
you to just get you up and running with
it
thank you guys for watching check out
some of my other videos and if you do i
will see you in the next one
[Music]
you