hey everyone welcome back to my Channel
today I'm going to challenge myself to
browse the web using only terminal
browser no mouse No Graphics just plain
text we all been there clicking from top
to another getting sidetracked by social
media or email
notifications and before you know it an
hour has passed and you still St on the
same web page
traditionally web browsing can be really
productivity killer with the content
noise of ads popups and suggested
content it's easy to get lost in the
mess and I found an answer to this
Linux this is a text based web browser
that's perfect for those who want to
browse the web without any
hustle today I'll show you how to
install links and give you a quick tour
of how to use it let's
[Music]
start let's focus on the Linux systems
and you can install links on the Windows
as well but for Windows um it's a bit
complicated not bit complicated but you
have to do extra step you have to
install
sigin H which is a large collection of
gnu and open-source tools and during the
installation process you have to select
links from the package list now now once
swing is installed you can launch links
through the swing
terminal but we will focus on the Linux
so for a dear or Ubuntu we are going to
use AP install for a red hat send OS
based systems we use umum or dnf for Arc
it's pack
Das capital S
links and for
maros brew install
links if you have home run
installed so as you can see on my screen
I have a Ubuntu machine it's a fresh
installation so the first thing we need
to do is to update system
now we need to install
links and in a few moments we will get
links
installed okay and installation finished
so let's clear the
screen now that we've installed links
let's go over how to use it to start
links open Terminal and type
links simply as
that TA down when you first launch links
you will see help screen now how would
you operate in that browser so there's a
few shortcuts a g for go to URL Q for
quit links arrows to navigate up and
down uh up and down going to the content
um forward and
backwards arrow to the right is go to
the link Arrow left is go back P is for
print or save the document slash for
seage within a page and a for add a book
bookmark so let's go to the website
press G and you can see there's a place
to type in url so we type
angry sis ops.com
click
enter and this is my page so now let's
press arrow down to go through the menu
and let let's say we want to see section
about me so now once I did arrow
down and it's highlighted you see it's
yellowish I press the arrow to the
right and under man is my page about me
as you can see this is the
content okay now I can press Arrow up to
go back and let's see if we go to
declaimer and we see the content is
there let's see another
um another page let's see what's the
articles for esxi AR to the right and we
can see that under category SX we have
few posts and we can continue to read
let's
see and there's a article
so as you can see it's quick it's fast
and it gives us information without any
hassle let's see maybe um the other page
let's go for G and let's
type
google.com it ask us for a cookie we
will allow it
and that's how the Google looks like
over here so here is a search
bar and we can
type angry
iss.com let's see and press enter s
Google there you are that's the links to
my website in the Google search uh let's
maybe search something
more
generate and there you are so as you can
see it's easy it's quick and without any
hassle okay guys that would be it for
today uh I hope hope I introduce you to
something new I hope uh that was
interesting as you can see you can work
in the terminal you don't need to leave
your terminal to browse the web uh to
quit links just press q and it ask you
do you want it why and you are back to
the terminal so without leaving terminal
you can browse the
web I think this deserve a like this
deserve to subscribe to my channel and
that will help to grow my channel it
cost you nothing you can always
unsubscribe but please do subscribe and
click on the notification Bell not to
miss another video and see you in
another one very soon bye
[Music]