This is an alternative way to generate a
function. Instead of finding every point
on the graph, here we are drawing all
the tangent lines first. Hidden in this
process lies an interesting duality
between points and lines. A duality that
also occurs between fundamental
quantities found in both classical
mechanics and thermodynamics.
By the end of this video, you will see
that all these dualities are really just
basic applications of one simple yet
powerful math trick known as the
Legendre transform.
The Legendre transform was developed in
by the French mathematical physicist
Adrien-Marie Legendre.
Just 50 years later in the mid-1830s,
William Rowan Hamilton used it to
introduce an entirely new formulation of
classical mechanics. A formulation that
built upon Newton and Lagrange's earlier
work and used as its starting point the
Legendre transform of the Lagrangian,
better known as the Hamiltonian. After
another 40 years or so passed, in 1878,
Josiah Willard Gibbs would use
Legendre's transform to generate three
extremely useful thermodynamic
quantities out of the internal energy.
Amazingly, what makes all of this
possible is just one main idea. All the
information about a function is stored
in its tangent lines. Or rather, to be
more precise, the Y intercepts of its
tangent lines.
How is this possible? And for which type
of functions is this true? We'll
discover the answers by considering a
few basic examples. Let's start with the
function f of x equals x squared.
Now, what kind of information is
actually contained in this function?
What we have here is the knowledge that
for any value of x, we can always assign
a specific value f of x. Our goal will
be to transform f from depending on x to
a new function that depends on some
other variable that we'll call p. But we
want to do it in such a way that no
information is lost in the process. The
way we'll do it is through the
derivative. If we take the derivative of
f, we get a new function that now
specifies the slope of the tangent line
at every point x.
We call this new function p, which is
dependent on x.
Now, in this specific example, for every
x, we get an entirely unique value of p.
This means that there's a one-to-one
correspondence between p and x, which
allows us to consider yet another
function x of p.
So, we have two ways of viewing things
here.
Either p as a function of x, or x as a
function of p.
We can then plug x directly into f,
making f now dependent on p.
It seems like we've succeeded, right? We
have transformed f from a function that
depends on x to a new function that
depends on p without losing any
information.
Not quite.
Look at what happens if we consider the
function f of x equals x minus d
squared. If we apply the same type of
reasoning, so we first find its
derivative,
solve for x as a function of p,
and then plug back into f,
we find the exact same result.
Whatever value we plug in for d here
will always lead to the same end
function. The information about d is
lost in the procedure we're currently
following.
The reason this occurs is because we've
only been considering the tangent lines
of each function,
which turn out to be the same
everywhere, just shifted.
Fortunately, there is a closely related
quantity that is able to capture the
uniqueness of each of these functions.
And that is the Y intercepts of the
tangent lines.
Which you can see actually do differ
depending on the original function.
So, taking this into account, we'll now
call this line f, which is just the line
from x to f of x.
And also define the value g as the
negative of the Y intercept.
Then recalling that p was just the
derivative,
we can use simple geometry to relate g
and f.
Finally, we arrive at a new function
that truly retains all the information
of the original.
And this new function is the Legendre
transform of f.
This is the general form of it. If we
apply it to our family of functions
we've been considering, we get the
following.
[Music]
As you can see from the equation on the
right, we have no longer lost
information about d.
It is only when d equals 0 that the
equation on the right reduces to the one
on the left. Since we've now
incorporated info about the Y intercepts
of tangent lines, each of the original
functions of x maps to a unique function
of p. And because no information has
been lost in this updated process, we
can also find the Legendre transform of
g,
and arrive back at the original f.
We now truly have two ways of expressing
the same information.
One that depends on the variable x, and
the other that depends on the variable
p.
Providing a beautiful duality between
points and lines.
So, we've discovered a way to apply this
transformation to a whole family of
functions of this particular form. But
what other functions can we apply it to?
To motivate the answer to this, we'll
consider one more basic example. Let's
see what happens if we try to apply the
Legendre transform to the function f of
x equals x cubed. We follow the same
steps as before. First, we find the
derivative and call it p of x. Then, we
try to solve for x as a function of p.
Immediately, we run into a problem. This
is not a function. Any value we plug in
for p will result in two different
values for x. What this means is that
there are many pairs of points that have
the same slope. We can see this visually
if we plot the derivative. With the
exception of the origin, we are always
able to find two points that have the
exact same value. And in terms of f of
x, these values correspond to producing
the exact same slope for two tangent
lines. This illustrates the key thing we
need in order to be able to find the
Legendre transform of a given function.
We need all the slopes of tangent lines
to be unique. And this will occur if the
function's derivative is essentially
always decreasing or increasing. The
technical math term is that it must be
monotonic. And there's also an entirely
equivalent way to say this in terms of
the original function f. In order for a
function f to have a Legendre transform,
it needs to be convex. Meaning that if
you connect any two points on the curve,
the line is always on the same side of
the curve.
Whether that's on top or below.
As soon as you find two points where
this behavior switches, it automatically
means that the function is not convex.
And there's no way to perform a Legendre
transform of the function. So, in
general, given any convex function, we
can always find the Legendre transform
of it by applying this formula with just
three simple steps. And since this
always produces a convex function g, we
are guaranteed to arrive back at the
original f whenever we apply the
Legendre transform to g.
Now, everything I've been saying applies
to convex functions of a single
variable.
This can be useful at times. However,
when generalized to functions of more
than one variable, it becomes much more
useful and applicable. All it requires
is to apply the product rule to what
we've already learned. For any pair of
variables x and y, we can multiply them
together and consider a tiny change in
their value or differential. By the
product rule, this equals x dy plus y
dx.
Similarly, if we have a function that
depends on both x and y, then we can
write its differential as follows.
Where this term means we take the
partial derivative of f with respect to
x while keeping y fixed, and this one is
the partial derivative with respect to y
while keeping x fixed. We can write this
in a nicer form if we call the first one
u and the second one v.
Now, what we'd like to do is to see if
it would be possible to construct a new
function g that instead of depending on
x and y, it rather depends on u and y.
So, its differential will be something
times du plus something times dy.
And in order to find this, the trick is
simply to subtract f from u times x,
which is really just the definition of
the Legendre transform we found earlier.
If we then take the differential of
this, we get dG = udx + xdu
dF.
Substituting for dF, we find the
following.
And since the differentials here are of
y and u, these are the two independent
variables of our new function G. The
final step is then to just use this
bottom equation to solve for x in terms
of u. If we do that, then we can replace
the x's above with terms that contain u
instead.
If we follow these steps for a convex
function F that depends on x and y, we
are guaranteed to arrive at a function G
that is dependent on u and y. Using
similar reasoning, we can also switch to
a new function of x and v,
or a function of u and v.
So, depending on how many independent
variables the original function depends
on,
there will be two to the n different
functions we can transform to. In order
to make this sink in and be a bit more
concrete, we'll now turn our attention
to how this shows up in physics.
Our first example will be from
thermodynamics.
One of the fundamental quantities in
thermodynamics is the internal energy U
of a physical system, which depends on
entropy, volume, and the number of
particles. As a differential, the
relations between all of these is
expressed as follows.
Now, there's another thermodynamic
quantity called the Helmholtz free
energy, which is defined by subtracting
T * S from U.
But, this is really just a Legendre
transform of the internal energy. In
physics, the sign convention is
sometimes reversed in order to make sure
certain physical quantities have the
correct sign. So, if we take the
differential of F now, we can see that
dF = dU - TdS - SdT. Substituting for dU
and canceling terms results in the
following,
which means that F is a function of V,
T, and N.
Now, remember, the Legendre transform
simply swaps variables and allows us to
keep all the same information contained
in the original function. So, whatever
physics is present in the internal
energy equation, the exact same physics
is captured by the Helmholtz free energy
equation. It's just that we now have two
options to use based on what our
experimental controls might be.
If we can control the entropy and
volume, then this is the equation to
use. But, if we instead can control the
temperature and volume, we have this
equation.
We can take one more step in this
process by doing another Legendre
transform to swap the volume for
pressure. This is done by subtracting
-PV from F.
We call this G, the Gibbs free energy.
Its differential is the following, and
substituting for dF results in this
expression.
So, the Gibbs free energy depends on
temperature, pressure, and particle
number.
Doing another Legendre transform,
subtracting -S * T from G,
we can get yet one more expression
called the enthalpy.
[Music]
The differential is then this,
and again substituting, we get the
following.
[Music]
So, the enthalpy is a function of
entropy, pressure, and particle number.
And finally, after applying one more
transform,
we arrive back at the internal energy.
[Music]
Let's now take a moment to consider what
all this means and appreciate just how
powerful the simple math trick of the
Legendre transform can be.
We have four different expressions here
that all contain the same information
about the physics of a thermodynamic
system. All we need is to know just one
of these, and by the Legendre transform,
we can generate the rest.
And in each case, we have different
control variables.
So, depending on your experimental
conditions and what you're able to
control,
the Legendre transform allows you to
start from any of these and arrive at
the one you actually need.
These equations also tell us that in a
state of thermal equilibrium, if the
entropy, volume, and particle number of
the system are constant, then we know
that internal energy is at a minimum.
Similarly, if the temperature, volume,
and number are constant, then the
Helmholtz free energy is at a minimum.
And of course, the same type of
reasoning applies to the Gibbs free
energy and enthalpy.
[Music]
Let's now consider how the Legendre
transform shows up in classical
mechanics. After Newton's initial
formulation of classical mechanics with
vectors,
there were two alternative versions
developed by Joseph Louis Lagrange and
William Rowan Hamilton. These
formulations removed vectors entirely
and instead turned solving physics
problems into pure algebraic
manipulation. The starting point for
Lagrangian mechanics is a quantity
called the Lagrangian, which is a
function of two variables, Q and Q-dot.
The starting point for Hamiltonian
mechanics is a function called the
Hamiltonian, which is defined by
subtracting L from P * Q-dot, where P is
the so-called generalized momentum,
defined as a partial derivative of L.
[Music]
And again, this is just a Legendre
transform. By swapping P and Q-dot, we
are able to transform from a function
dependent on Q and Q-dot
to another dependent on Q and P. You can
see exactly how this happens with a very
basic example. Imagine a ball in free
fall.
So, it's only under the influence of
gravity. If Q is in this direction, then
its Lagrangian is given by the following
expression, which implies that the
Hamiltonian is given by this expression.
[Music]
Then, using the definition of
generalized momentum
and reducing,
we really can express H purely as a
function of Q and P.
Going back to the more general case, we
can use this expression to write down
the differential of H.
But, L is a function of Q and Q-dot, so
dL should equal the following.
And since H is really just a function of
Q and P, its differential can be
similarly expressed as follows.
[Music]
Canceling and setting like terms equal
to each other,
we discover the famous Hamilton's
equations. These are the equations of
motion for a system described by
Hamiltonian mechanics. They contain the
exact same information that is contained
in the Euler-Lagrange equations, which
is how you get the equations of motion
in Lagrangian mechanics.
And just as we went from the Lagrangian
to the Hamiltonian, we can also apply
the Legendre transform to the
Hamiltonian and arrive back at the
Lagrangian.
So, this seemingly simple math trick
proves to be extremely powerful. It
provides a very useful way to swap
different variables and still keep all
the information about a function, truly
capturing the duality between points and
lines, various thermodynamic potentials,
and even two different formulations of
classical mechanics. If you've stuck
around to the end, I first want to say
thank you for watching this video and
for already supporting the channel.
I'd also like to invite you to consider
joining my new Patreon community. I'll
be posting there regularly to get your
feedback. So, if you want to weigh in on
video topics, animations I'm working on,
or even thumbnail design, that's the
place to go. You'll also get early
access to content, help shape final
edits, and most of all, contribute to
making higher math and physics
accessible to more people. So, if you're
at all interested and financially able
to do so,
please consider joining.
Thanks again, and remember to always
abide by reason.