Hey guys, do you want to control your
Gmail account from the terminal? Well,
in this video, I'll show you how you can
do it. We'll use a free service called
Mail Slurp to connect our Gmail account
and then control it in code. So, here is
my email account. And I want to connect
this to Mail Slurp so that we can access
it via the terminal. And if I go to the
Mailer dashboard at app.mails.com,
I can click on inboxes and I can create
a connection to my Gmail account. Here
you can see a connect Gmail button. I'm
going to click that.
Next, I can pick a Gmail account. I'm
going to pick this case artifact one. It
will ask me if I want to continue.
And my email account is connected to
Mail Slip. So now I can view all my
emails and attachments here in the mail
app. But I can also control this Gmail
inbox using code. So if I go to the
developers page here, I can see a API
key and ways to integrate this inbox
into my code. So I'm going to copy this
API key and next we'll turn to the
terminal to show us how to read emails.
Okay, here I am in the terminal. So I'm
going to export my API key as a variable
called key in my terminal. And here I'm
using uh the bash terminal on Windows,
but this applies for any terminal you
want to use. Okay. And now that we have
our key enabled, we can call the Mailip
API like so. So we can say curl
api.mmal.com/inboxes
and then we pass in our API key as a
header with X API key. If I hit that, I
can see the inboxes I have added. So
here is my email address, my Gmail
account, and it has an ID here. So if we
want to list the emails in this inbox,
we can use the ID to do so. So let's do
that now. I'm going to copy this. Copy
that. Clear that. And now I'm going to
type in curl
um api.mmailslope.com/inboxes
the id then emails and then I'm going to
put in my header. So uh x
so - h and then x api key and put in my
key.
And here I can see my emails. So to
verify this we could look uh security
alert is one of them and if I go to my
actual Gmail account now we can see this
security alert email is in my Gmail
account. So we just managed to view our
Gmail account in the terminal. What else
can we do with the mailer API? So for
this we need to consult the mailer
documentation to find uh other methods.
So if I go to docs.mmailserb.com
and I click on the API specs here I can
see all the methods available for
sending and receiving emails with our
Gmail connection. I'm going to click on
um swagger UI. This is a a nice way to
explore the API. And if I look in the
inbox controller I can see this method
here. inboxes inbox id /confirm with a
post request will allow us to send an
email. So here I can see some example uh
JSON being sent. So in order to send
that in curl uh we just need to send a
body like this. So back in my terminal
let's write a way to send an email. So I
can say curl and we're going to use the
method post and then we're going to send
it to api.mmailser.com/inboxes
and then we want the inbox ID and
confirm because we want to get a
confirmation after we send. And we also
want to pass in our header. So we're
going to say X API key and then pass in
the key like that. And we also want to
pass in some data. Um so we're going to
pass JSON. So we'll put a um content
type header application JSON like that.
And now we want our data and we are
going to use single quotes to put our
JSON inside. And we will say um two.
So we'll put two and we want an array of
addresses here. So I'm just going to
send an email to uh our own inbox um to
test the sending. And we'll put a
subject um test. Oh, we need to use uh
quotes around that
subject.
Say test email
and a body.
We'll say hello from test. Okay, let's
try this and see if it works.
Okay, I'm missing a quote somewhere in
my body. Aha, it is actually here. So,
we got to put quotes around JSON
properties.
Press okay.
and we get a confirmation. So, our email
has sent. If we scroll back up, we can
see that there is a um ID for the sent
email and it's from my email address to
my email address. So, to confirm that,
we could look back in our email account.
I have it connected here in Outlook
and here I can see the test. So, hello
from test. So, we were just able to send
an email from our Gmail account using
the terminal. So, this is a really
powerful tool that you can use anywhere
for automation, scripting, tests, or
little tools you want to use with your
own email account. So, for more
information, see mailer.com and sign up
for a free account