There is a prequel to the Da Vinci Code.
It's called Angels and Demons. And in
it, terrorists steal 1/8 of a gram of
antimatter from CERN to try to blow up
the Vatican. Because the thing is, when
antimatter and matter meet, they
annihilate, turning nearly 100% of their
combined mass into pure energy. This is
via E= MC². It is the most violent
process physics allows.
>> Let's go.
Oh my god.
>> Now that was just a novel, but CERN
actually is making antimatter
and we got to visit it.
>> This is CERN's antimatter factory.
There's anti-roton going beneath our
feet.
>> They are under our feet at this time.
Here, protons are accelerated up to
99.93%
the speed of light and smashed into an
aridium target to produce 20 million
anti-rotons every minute. This is so
much bigger than I was thinking. This is
crazy. Antimatter is the most expensive
substance in the universe. 1 billion per
gram.
>> No way. Go up. We are missing zeros
here.
>> And CERN makes it to do something that
seems impossible. So, you're making
anti-atoms?
>> Yes.
>> CERN made the first anti-hydrogen atoms
back in 1995, but they quickly ran into
a problem because those anti-atoms only
survived for 40 billionth of a second
before annihilating, which is way too
short to do anything useful with it. If
only they could figure out how to store
antimatter, then they could study it and
try to find ways in which it might
differ from normal matter. They knew
that any unexpected difference could
reveal entirely new physics. So, how do
you store antimatter in a world full of
matter? Well, that's one of the problems
CERN has been obsessing over for the
last 30 plus years. It has allowed them
to do some of the most precise tests of
antimatter to date. And they even
managed to trap antimatter in a box,
load it onto a truck, and ship it. And
they are doing all of this to try and
solve one of the biggest unsolved
mysteries in all of physics. To
understand it, we must go back to a
discovery made around 100 years ago.
Previously on Veritasium, we learned how
a strange physicist Paul the Rock came
up with an equation to unite special
relativity with quantum mechanics. It
worked surprisingly well, but The Rock
was stumped by his own equation because
the solution for an electron at rest was
kind of strange. There were two possible
energies, E= MC^2 and E= minus MC^2. But
how could an electron have negative
energy? Well, instead of throwing away
his negative energy solution, The Rock
ended up proposing something radical.
This negative energy solution
corresponded to an entirely new particle
unknown to physics at the time. It would
have the same mass as an electron but
carry opposite charge. It would be an
anti-electron or positron. Miraculously,
a year later, the first posetron was
observed by accident in nature. Over the
following decades, physicists built on
the rock's equation to form an entirely
new framework of quantum mechanics.
quantum field theory. This didn't just
explain why there are antiparticles, but
it also answered a more fundamental
question, which is why is every electron
in the universe exactly the same? The
answer began to take shape when people
figured out that fundamental particles
aren't just particles or waves, but
rather excitations of a quantum field.
So you'd have an electron field that
permeates all of space. And this field
can get excited, but only in identical
discrete units, each with the same mass,
spin, and charge. And that's why every
electron is the same. They're all
excitations of the same field. Now, you
could have several excitations, that
would be several electrons, and they can
move around, too. The only requirement
is that they can never overlap exactly.
Of course, there is nothing special
about this kind of excitation. You could
just as well have a mirror opposite. In
fact, the equations that describe this
field require such excitations to exist.
They have the same mass and spin but
with opposite charge. This is the idea
of an anti-electron or posetron.
It's exactly what that minus sign in the
rock's equation was revealing. And just
like an electron, posetrons can move
around, too. Only posetrons can overlap
with electrons. But watch what happens
when they do. Now, I'm simplifying a
little here, but because they're each
other's mirror images, the opposite
charges cancel each other out. The
excitations disappear and the field
returns back to its ground state. But
that would predict that the particles
just disappear. So, how is that
possible? Where did the mass go? Well,
the only way this could work is if that
mass got converted into something else,
energy according to E= MC². The energy
got transferred into a different quantum
field, the photon field. And that is
what we mean by annihilation.
Now, people realize that most
fundamental particles could be described
using the same approach where each could
be seen as an excitation of their very
own quantum field. Now, this meant two
things. The first is that most particles
must have an antiparticle twin because
they're just mirror excitations in the
same field. There are some exceptions
though, like the photon and hig boson,
which are their own antiparticle. And
the second and more important
implication is that each antiparticle
must be exactly equal to a normal
particle just with the opposite charge.
But then around the mid1 1960s, people
realized that there was a big issue with
this explanation. And it all stemmed
from how it fit in with the newly
accepted big bang theory.
In the very first moments after the big
bang, the universe was extremely hot and
dense and photons had so much energy
that the reverse process of annihilation
happened. So two photons could come
together and spontaneously convert their
energy into the mass and kinetic energy
of a particle antiparticle pair. And so
the universe was filled with these pairs
continuously popping into and out of
existence. But as the universe continued
to expand, it cooled and those photons
lost energy until around 3 seconds after
the big bang, they had lost so much
energy that pair production stopped.
And this is what troubled physicists in
the 1960s because they believe that in
those initial stages an equal amount of
matter and antimatter should have been
created. But if an equal amount of
matter and antimatter were created then
every particle should have found its
antiparticle twin and annihilated
meaning there should be no stuff around
us. No matter and no antimatter just
photons only radiation. So this became
known as the big bang radiation
catastrophe
because clearly when we look around us
we see a lot more than just energy. The
universe is filled with matter. But how
can that be? Why is there now more
matter than antimatter in the universe?
Where did that asymmetry come from?
Well, that is one of the biggest
unsolved mysteries in all of physics.
Initially, some people tried to brush
this away and they argued that perhaps
there is no asymmetry at all.
>> Maybe we happen to be in a pocket that
because of blind random chance, some
reasonable statistical fluctuations
where most surrounded by matter and
there' be some region that would again
be like like a Marvel movie, like some
mirror universe, there would be mo
slightly, you know, imbalance in the
other direction.
>> Paul the Rock seemed to have favored
this approach. He argued that there
might be entire anti-stars and he ended
his 1943 Nobel lecture by saying there
may be half the stars of each kind. The
two kinds of stars would both show
exactly the same spectra and there would
be no way of distinguishing them by
present astronomical methods. Physicist
Edward Harrison took this one step
further, saying there should even be
entire anti-galaxies.
And then people realize, well, if that's
the case, there'd be regions where these
boundaries where the two regions would
meet, and that should be lighting up the
sky. Should be tons of matter,
antimatter annihilations. Should be tons
of of very high energy light. So, people
surfed the sky looking for these hot
spots, but they didn't find any. And so,
this possibility was ruled out. There
really is more matter than antimatter in
our universe. There really is an
asymmetry. So the next obvious question
is well how large is that asymmetry? If
we go back to around 10 seconds after
the big bang we can figure it out. By
this time pair production had long
stopped a full 7 seconds ago and by now
just about every antiparticle had
annihilated with its particle
counterpart and turned into photons.
Now, the universe was filled with just
some leftover particles like electrons
and protons whizzing around at
incredible speeds and those remnant
photons. But because these electrons and
protons were traveling so fast, they
couldn't come together to form atoms.
So, you had this plasma of charged
particles and that meant that when
photons were going around, they
scattered off those charged particles.
So, they couldn't travel very far
without interacting with matter. That
all changed around 380,000 years after
the Big Bang. By now, the electrons and
protons had slowed down enough to form
neutral atoms, and photons could only be
absorbed by electrons in atoms if they
had exactly the right energy to move the
electron up an energy level. In
practice, this meant that photons could
now basically travel through space
unimpeded.
Those atoms then went on to form all the
stars and galaxies, and those photons
stuck around, too. They've gone on to
make up the low-level radiation that
permeates the entire observable
universe, the cosmic microwave
background or CMB.
And when we estimate the total number of
photons in that CMB, we find that there
are about 10 to the 89. And because
almost all of those photons were
originally created during those very
first seconds after the big bang, that
original annihilation, we can infer that
there must originally have been around
10 to the 89 particles and
antiparticles.
Now, we can also estimate how many
ordinary matter particles like protons
and neutrons there are in the observable
universe today. The ones that survived
that annihilation. And what we find is
that there are about 10 to the 80 So
that means that for every billion
antimatter particles and billion matter
particles there were in the early
universe when they annihilated they did
so almost perfectly. But there was one
one out of a billion matter particles
that somehow survived. And everything we
see around us today is a descendant of
those lucky one in a billion particles.
Every person, animal, jungle, and ocean,
every asteroid colliding or galaxy
spiraling, every single dot of light in
the night sky is made up of one of those
lucky one in a billion particles.
And that brings us to the craziest part
because it tells us that there must be a
difference between matter and antimatter
and how they evolve according to the
laws of physics. But it's not just any
difference. No, it would make sense if
they behaved completely different. I
mean, you would just have different laws
of physics governing each type of
particle or it would make sense if they
were governed by the exact same laws.
But in that case, there would be no
difference. It would be completely
symmetric. What's really weird here is
that the laws are almost exactly the
same, but with a tiny difference. And
that doesn't make any sense.
For the past 70 years, physicists have
tried to explain where this asymmetry
comes from. But so far, all attempts
have failed. And part of the reason this
has been so difficult is because our
laws of physics are full of symmetry.
In the mid 1950s, there were three
symmetries all particles were believed
to obey. Charge, par, and time reversal
symmetry. Charge symmetry is super
simple. It just means that if you swap
all positive charges with negative ones
and vice versa, then the interactions
don't change. In other words, there is
nothing special about a positive or
negative charge. Just that one is
exactly equal and opposite to the other.
To understand parity symmetry, consider
this mirror which creates a sort of
parallel universe where everything is
the same but reflected. So my left hand
becomes my right hand and vice versa.
Now take this molecule here which is
llanine an important amino acid we need
to make proteins. Now that L is in its
name because the amine group this NH2
part over here is on the left but in the
mirror you see its sister molecule
dlanine that NH2 part is now on the
right. And if you try to make elanine in
a lab you'll find that you'll get 50%
llanine and 50% dlanine. In other words,
there is no experiment you could do that
determines whether you're in our
universe or in the mirror universe. And
the same is true for many left and
right-handed molecules. If you just try
to make them normally in a lab, you'll
get 50% of each. So, our universe
doesn't favor left or right-handedness.
Lastly, time reversal symmetry means
that the laws of physics work the same
whether time is running forwards or
backwards. Now, out of all of these,
time reversal symmetry might feel
strange because there are many things
that clearly don't work backwards in
time. You can't uncook an egg,
unshhatter a wine glass, or turn a plant
back into a seat. But all of these
follow from the second law of
thermodynamics, which describes how many
interacting particles evolve from less
likely states, typically more ordered,
to more likely states, typically a mess.
But this is a statistical law. It's not
a fundamental law of physics. If you
zoom in to the level of individual
particles, then every interaction is
perfectly reversible. You can tell
whether these collisions happen forwards
or backwards in time. Now, the
combination of all of these symmetries
combined is called CPT symmetry. And CPT
symmetry, it turns out, is kind of a big
deal.
>> What happens if CPT gets broken?
>> Well, literally cats and dogs start
living together. Time flows backwards.
all kinds of things start uh breaking in
our in our description of nature. Now,
one of the reasons why why CPT and the
standard model go so well together is
because it really is built into the very
structure of special relativity.
>> Special relativity is built on one core
principle which is that the laws of
physics are the same for all inertial
observers and this includes any
measurement they make of the speed of
light.
In the 1950s, Julian Schwinger, Hardert
Lutters, and Wolffrang Pi proved that if
our universe obeys this principle, which
we strongly believe it does, then it
must be CPT symmetric. But the reverse
is also true. If you break CPT symmetry,
then this core principle also breaks.
And that's where things get tricky
because after the Rock united special
relativity with quantum mechanics, all
following quantum theories also
incorporated special relativity. And so
our best theories of reality, quantum
field theory and the standard model are
built on that exact same principle. So
now we have a paradox because on the one
hand we need a symmetry to explain why
we're here. But on the other hand, if
CPT symmetry breaks, it tears down our
best theories with it. So physicists
started off on a hunt for a special kind
of asymmetry. an asymmetry that could
explain that one in a billion
discrepancy while also maintaining the
larger CPT symmetry. The first clue that
such as might exist came in the mid1
1950s. Up until then, every interaction
that had been studied conserved the
individual symmetries of CP and T and so
conserved CPT as a whole. But in 1956,
theoretical physicists Sunung Da and
Chen Niny Young realized that no one had
checked whether parity is conserved in
the weak nuclear force. So they set out
to test whether the universe favored
left or right-handedness.
And to do it, they enlisted the help of
one of Lee's colleagues, one of the
world's best experimentalists, Chen
Shung Buu, also known as Madame Wu. Once
the idea of the experiment was pitched
to her, then she just went all in. She
canceled trips. She worked straight over
holiday breaks. It was really a a all
hands-on deck operation over a very
frenzied few months. When Powi learned
of the experiment, he said, "I do not
believe that the Lord is a weak
left-hander, and I am ready to bet a
very high sum that the experiments will
give symmetric results."
Now, all that was left to do was run the
experiment. It worked something like
this. She started with cobalt 60, an
isotope of cobalt where the nucleus has
an intrinsic angular momentum or spin.
When she applied a strong magnetic
field, she forced all the spins to point
in the same direction. But cobalt 60 is
also radioactive. So every once in a
while a neutron inside one of its nuclei
decays into a proton releasing an
electron and anti-utrino and leaving a
nickel 60 atom behind. Now the electrons
emitted could travel in two directions.
They could either go in the same
direction as the nuclear spin or they
could go in the opposite way. But if
spin is clockwise in our universe, then
it is also clockwise when reflected in
the mirror. Which means it points in the
same direction in both universes. So the
only way the experiment could be the
same in our universe and the mirror
universe is if the electrons were
emitted in equal amounts in each
direction. It should be 50% on each
side. But what Wu actually found was
that around 60% of the electrons moved
in the opposite direction to the nuclear
spin, which would mean that 60% moved in
the same direction as the nuclear spin
in the mirror universe. But that meant
that there is an experiment you could do
to tell whether you're in our universe
or the mirror universe. So it proved
that par is not conserved. This shocked
the physics community.
PI upon being informed of the results
exclaimed that's total nonsense.
>> Very smart people Nobel laureates said
that can't be right. Do it again. I
don't believe it. I you know and and in
a sense you can see where they're coming
from. There had been no hint as yet that
the that that kind of the universe would
care whether I'm looking at myself you
know in a mirror or not.
>> So others repeated the experiment and by
1957 there was no further room for
doubt. God really was a weak
left-hander.
That same year, Lee and Young won the
Nobel Prize in physics for the discovery
of parity violation, but Wu's name was
left off. Lee and Young acknowledged her
during their speech and tried to get her
nominated for a prize another year. But
the Nobel Committee never honored her.
In a way, she was robbed of the Nobel
Prize. 1988 winner Jack Steinberger
called this the biggest mistake in the
Nobel Committee's history. But her work
had done something important. It had
cast doubt on the long-held belief that
charge parity and time reversal were
fundamental symmetries of our universe.
This made many physicists uncomfortable.
So they came up with a workaround. Maybe
it's okay if parity symmetry was broken
because that's not a fundamental
symmetry of nature. It's just part of a
larger symmetry charge par. The idea was
that if you reflected everything in a
mirror and swapped all the particles for
their antiparticles, then the symmetry
would be restored and all would be good
again.
But then 7 years later, two physicists
found that some particles also violated
the combined charge parity symmetry. Now
physicists were getting really nervous.
Two symmetries that they believed were
fundamental parts of our universe were
broken. So the next big question on
everyone's mind was is CPT symmetry also
going to fail and take down the standard
model with it. Then in 1973 something
seemingly miraculous happened. Makot
Kobayashi and Toshihida Mascawa found a
way to explain all the observed P and CP
violation while maintaining CPT symmetry
and it all fit directly within the
standard model. The only issue is that
when it comes to the matter antimatter
asymmetry, it can only account for an
asymmetry of 10 to the minus 18, which
is a billion times less than we need to
explain the observed matter antimatter
asymmetry.
So the ingredients are there, which is
cool cuz we didn't think even the
ingredients were there,
>> but they're not there in a large enough
strength. You don't have a strong enough
rate of CP violation if you just strict
with stick with strictly the standard
model. And so are people now getting
nervous about CPT?
>> Not nervous, I'd say excited.
>> And that's because this means there is
likely new physics beyond the standard
model. But to find out what that might
be, we must study antimatter up close to
see if there are any ways in which it
might be different from normal matter.
Ways that could explain that asymmetry.
So you know where we're going.
>> Oh. Oh, look. There it is. CERN, baby.
Woo! CERN is best known for the Large
Hadron Collider, a 27 km underground
ring where protons are accelerated up to
99.9999%
the speed of light. Beams traveling in
opposite directions are smashed
together, releasing huge amounts of
energy. It's the closest we get to the
high energy conditions of the early
universe. But at the southern edge of
the LHC, there is a smaller proton
accelerator called the proton synretron.
Protons in this ring are only
accelerated to 99.93%
the speed of light. And some of that
proton beam is fed out of the ring and
ends up here. This is CERN's antimatter
factory. And in here you make
anti-rotons. How many?
>> Uh, usually it's around 40 million every
couple of minutes. We are now going to
enter the facility by actually a
technical building which is not very
interesting to watch.
>> I find this all interesting to watch.
>> To make sure we're safe, we always had
to carry around these devices. So,
you've got two what are they called?
>> Theimters.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Just to be safe.
>> These are standard devices to measure
the amount of uh dose of radiation that
you get. This is a supervised radiation
environment which means it's it's an
environment in which we keep an eye onto
the amount of radiation we get as
radiation workers.
>> Where are we going now?
>> So now we are going to enter into the
main building.
>> There's antimatter behind this behind
this door.
>> Yes. Under our feet.
>> Oh wow.
>> Yeah. We'll see. You'll see.
>> Please guys, this is
this is a huge place.
This is so much bigger than I was
thinking.
This is crazy.
Well, I feel like I'm a kid in a candy
store looking at this.
>> This place is pretty It's pretty fun,
huh? The first time you see it.
>> Yeah, it's so impressive.
>> Here you see pretty much the scheme of
how this facility is working. You get
protons coming from one of the CERN
accelerators, the the PS, which smash
onto a target. The protons are
accelerated up to around 99.93%
the speed of light and have energies up
to 26 ga electron volts. They're aimed
at a remarkably small target, an iridium
rod 3 mm in diameter and 55 mm across
which itself is embedded in a graphite
and then in a titanium alloy structure.
Iridium was chosen because it's the
second densest element on Earth. And
that means that there are a lot of
nuclei packed in a small space, which
increases the odds that the protons will
hit something. But when one of these
protons hits an aridium nucleus, it
doesn't bounce off like you'd expect in
most collisions. It is going so fast and
has so much energy that it penetrates
the nucleus where it collides directly
with one of the neutrons or protons. And
to understand what happens next, we need
to look at what's going on inside the
proton. Because a proton is not a
fundamental particle. Instead, it is
made up of three fundamental particles
known as quarks. Specifically, two up
and one down quark. Those quarks whiz
around close to the speed of light. So
to keep all those quirks contained,
traveling at such incredible speeds and
in such a small space requires a very
strong force, which is why it's called
the strong force. And it's mediated by
particles known as gluons. You can think
of this force as acting like a rubber
band. But you can bring this past its
breaking point. If you keep putting in
energy, then you can put in so much
energy that another quark anti-quark
pair will be created. This bond breaking
into pair creation can happen several
times in a row and results in this sort
of shower of quark anti-quark pairs. And
a similar thing happens when a proton
collides with a neutron or proton inside
an aridium nucleus. Now most of those
pairs stay just like that pairs and they
travel off. But occasionally you will
get two anti-up and one anti-own quark
to come close enough and they form a new
particle made of free anti-quarks. They
form an anti-roton and their
counterparts will go on to form a
proton.
Now all of this this entire process from
initial collision to the shower of
particles and the formation of the
anti-roton happened in the span of 10 to
the minus23 seconds. That is a 100
billion trillionth of a second. It is
absolutely insane. And every time you
hit the target, you get trillions of
these collisions. And out the other side
comes a chaotic spray of protons,
anti-roton, and a bunch of other
particles all traveling at around 96%
the speed of light. Magnets then filter
out the anti-rotons from the other
particles, and they're sent on to the
next stage. And then we collect these
anti-rotons, bring them into the ring,
the anti-roton decelerator ring, which
is the one we are staring on top of. And
then they they circulate in the ID for a
while while they get cooled down. So the
idea here is really that we get these
antirotons every 2 minutes more or less.
It's about 30 million of them.
>> How expensive is it antimatter?
>> Look guys, what is what is value? It's a
bit difficult to evaluate it, right? For
sure. It's probably the most expensive
state of matter we can build on Earth
today.
>> How about I name some numbers and you
tell me if it's cheap or too expensive?
>> Shoot.
>> $1 billion per gram.
>> No way.
>> It's too cheap.
>> Orders of magnitude too cheap. But many
orders of
>> mag. That's what I was thinking. $100
billion per gram.
>> No way. Go up. I think uh probably you
miss other three zeros. free zeros.
>> I think so. Per gram. Yes. At least.
>> If you're wondering what you would do
with all that money, you should check
out today's video sponsor, SoFi. SoFi is
an all-in-one finance app that lets you
bank, borrow, and invest. And with their
premium membership, SoFi Plus, you get
benefits such as investment matches,
unlimited access to financial planners,
and a competitive APY on savings to earn
interest on your money. All so you can
let your money work for you. By adding
up all of these benefits, you could
unlock $1,000 or more in annual value
with qualifying activities. Of course,
it depends on how you use the app, so
check if it's right for you. And you can
get started by subscribing to SoFi Plus
for just $10 per month. Right now,
they're also running a promotion for US
residents. So, if you join SoFi Plus
between now and April 15th, you'll
automatically be entered into their
giveaway for a chance to win $75,000
as well as other cash prizes and free
memberships. So, to check out SoFi Plus,
head to sofi.com/varitasium
or click the link in the description.
I'd like to thank SoFi for sponsoring
this video. And now, back to antimatter.
There's anti-roton going beneath our
feet.
>> They are under our feet at this time.
Yes, indeed.
>> And it's not dangerous.
>> No, no, it's not dangerous. There's no
risk whatsoever.
>> Strong electric fields in the
decelerator slow down the anti-rotons
from 96% to 10% the speed of light. But
that's still about 100 million kmh.
To do experiments with them, they need
to be slowed down more.
Initially, this was done in a kind of
crazy way. The anti-proton beam was
fired at a thin plastic foil which
annihilated 99.9% of all the anti-roton.
But around 0.1% of those anti-rotons
survived and they came out slow enough
to do experiments with them. Of course,
this was very inefficient. And so in
2015 and 2016, a secondary ring called
Elena was installed. Elena slows the
anti-rotons to 1.5% the speed of light.
A nice slow 16.2 million kilometers per
hour.
>> This is running.
>> You are watching a live anti-roton
machine.
>> Are the anti-rotons going around in
these circles?
>> Exactly. The blue devices are magnets,
dipole magnets, which by lawren force
make the particles turn. Then you have
the orange ones which are quadruple
magnets which manage the focusing of
this beam. They're like lenses for
particles. It's a pretty pretty thin
pipe almost that they go for.
>> Yeah. I mean, you don't need much there,
right? Because as long as you don't bend
the particles, they just want to go
straight. You need to keep good vacuum
in there. Very good vacuum in fact.
Otherwise, they would anhilate.
>> And how often do you have annihilations
in this loop
>> in here?
>> Yeah. Because you can't have perfect
vacuum.
>> Well, no. No. you have a bit of losses
but you know the entire process of
catching I mean from the moment of
catching to the moment of extraction to
the experiments I think these days we
are about 86% efficiency they have made
it very efficient
after the anti-roton have been slowed
down in Alena they are sent onto five
different experiments each of which is
designed to study different properties
of antimatter to try and find ways in
which antimatter behaves differently
from normal matter
One of the first experiments that was
done which happened before the
antimatter factory was built was testing
whether the mass of a proton and
anti-roton are the same. But to do that
it brings us back to our original
problem. How do you store antimatter?
The way they solve this problem is
pretty clever. They started with a tube
which was pumped down to a vacuum. A
superconducting magnet sits around this
tube and it creates a magnetic field
that confines charged particles to the
center. At the same time, electrodes
generate electric fields that function
as endcaps, preventing the particles
from escaping out the ends. The whole
tube is then cooled down to around 4 kel
or -269°.
This causes almost all the remaining
particles to condense and freeze,
resulting in a vacuum pressure
comparable to outer space. So now they
could fill this tube with something like
anti-roton. And once inside, those
anti-rotons have nothing to annihilate
with and nowhere to go. They are
trapped. They had just built a real life
antimatter trap. The technical term for
this is a penning trap after France
penning whose work inspired the first
one. Fittingly, the team that did this
at CERN was called trap. With the
anti-roton trapped, they measured the
charge to mass ratio of the anti-roton
and compared it to that of the proton
and they found it was equal to one part
in 10 billion. Now, the pinning traps
made studying antimatter much easier,
and so it became a key tool that the
other experiments at the factory
adopted. In 2017, the base experiment
used it to measure the anti-roton's
magnetic moment, and they found that
within their level of accuracy, it was
equal and opposite to that of the
proton. So, thus far, everything was
behaving just as predicted. But there is
one force that they hadn't directly
probed yet. Gravity.
gravity. Could that be part of the
solution?
>> It very likely will be. Ultimately, part
of why is because gravity does not obey
the rules of special relativity, which
means it doesn't have to obey the CPT
theorem like the SE model does. And so,
in principle, that's um an area within
which one could more naturally expect
larger values of violations of C and CP
and and so on or even a CPT altogether.
In fact, back in the 1950s, a few
physicists entertained the idea of
anti-gravity, that antimatter would be
gravitationally repulsive. So, while
matter falls down in the Earth's
gravitational field, antimatter would
rise up. You had a basketball made of
antimatter, that would be easy to test,
but getting a basketball of antimatter
without it blowing up on you is pretty
hard. So,
it's it's not an easy thing to do um
gravity experiments on particles. You
can't just drop an anti-roton and see if
it falls because anti-rotons are
negatively charged and the electric
force is much stronger than gravity. So
even small stray electric fields would
influence them way more than gravity
would. So what you need is something
neutral. What you need is an anti-atom.
>> So you're making anti-atoms.
>> Yes.
>> How do you make the anti-atom? So what
we do is we we use antipotons and
posetrons
basically we merge them they become
antihydrogen.
>> Now there are several ways to make
antihydrogen and different experiments
do it in different ways but for Gar it
all starts here in this bunker.
>> In this bunker we have a small
accelerator. So we make our ourselves
our positrons
and then we capture them in a trap here.
They accelerate a beam of electrons up
to 99.9%
the speed of light and then fire those
at a tungsten target. Now while tungsten
itself is electrically neutral at the
high speed those electrons enter the
tungsten they get close enough to the
nuclei that the electron cloud can no
longer screen the intense positive
charge within. Thus, these nuclei create
strong electric fields, and those fields
then yank the electrons around, causing
them to rapidly decelerate as if they've
just slammed on the brakes. But the
thing is, when these electrons break,
they lose energy by emitting photons.
The Germans have a great word for this.
It's called Brealum or breaking
radiation. This breaking radiation
produces a wide range of photons ranging
from low energy X-rays all the way up to
nearly 9 mega electron volt gamma rays.
Now, out of all of these photons, it's
the gamma rays above roughly one mega
electron fold that are important because
when one of these gamma rays passes
close to a tungsten nucleus, there's a
chance that it transfers its momentum to
that nucleus and converts all its energy
into the mass and kinetic energy of an
electron posetron pair. But
unfortunately, this isn't a clean
process that just makes electron
posetron pairs. It produce posetrons but
it also produce a lot of photons, gamma
rays, neutrons and these are deadly
>> and that particle mass creates two
problems. The first is that deadly
radiation
>> supposed to be one of the highest
strongest source of radiation at sun.
>> This is one of the highest.
>> Yes. If you enter while it is working
you die in 10 seconds.
>> You die in 10 seconds.
>> You cannot escape.
>> It's terrifying. You melt from inside.
>> You melt from inside. You're saying that
way too casually.
>> And the second problem is that what
comes out of the tungsten isn't a nice
uniform beam of posetrons. Instead, you
get a shower of electrons, neutrons,
posetrons, and photons all mixed
together, all traveling at different
angles and different speeds.
The first problem is solved by encasing
the entire setup with massive 1.2 2 m
thick, 67% concrete, and 33% iron
blocks.
>> And this is enough to shield us.
>> Yes,
>> because it's photons.
>> Yes. This is 1,400 tons.
>> Okay. Okay. I feel a bit better now. Is
it running now?
>> No. But even if it runs, we can see just
outside and it's okay.
>> Okay. So, we're safe. You wear your
>> your badge.
Okay. So, you would know.
>> Yeah. But I guess 10 seconds, not
>> too late.
>> Too late.
>> Solving the second problem is a little
more involved. And it's honestly one of
the coolest combinations of physics and
engineering I've ever come across. So
strap in. When the posetrons leave the
tungsten target, some are traveling at a
few% the speed of light, while others
are traveling at more than 90% the speed
of light. Now, this massive spread makes
it very hard to work with. So, we need
to slow them down to around 0.34%
the speed of light or around 3.7 million
km hour. The way they do this is kind of
crazy because they shoot the positrons.
Remember those are antiparticles at a
mesh of ultra fine 20 micrometer
diameter tungsten wires which of course
are made of normal matter. When a fast
posetron enters the tungsten wire, it
immediately loses energy due to
scattering off the tungsten atoms. And
this happens so fast that within around
10 picos seconds, that is 10 trillionths
of a second, the posetron has slowed
down to match the thermal energy of the
tungsten.
But now the posetron is still trapped
inside the wire. So from here on,
through a random walk of collisions and
scattering, it needs to find its way
out. And if it bumps into an electron or
gets stuck in a defect, it never makes
it out. So you might expect almost none
of these posetrons to make it out and
for almost all of them to find an
electron and annihilate. And you'd be
right. The efficiency of this process is
terrible. For every thousand fast
posetrons entering the mesh, only about
one comes out as a usable slow posetron.
Another problem is that these posetrons
don't come out as a nice organized beam.
Instead, they are emitted at all kinds
of angles. So, we need to find a way to
focus them. This is done by letting the
shower of particles go through a
solenoid, which is a long coiled wire
with a current running through. That
current creates a magnetic field inside
the coil that acts as a magnetic lens
and focuses the posetrons.
This lets us capture many of the
posetrons emitted at wide angles that
would otherwise be lost.
But right now we still have a mix of
posetrons, electrons, neutrons, and
photons. So the next step is to separate
these. To do this, we use another
magnetic field. This curves the
electrons one way into a beam dump. The
photons and neutrons because they have
no electric charge are unaffected. So
they go straight through and are
absorbed by shielding. And the posetrons
because of their positive charge curve
the opposite way to electrons and they
go on to the next stage. Now we're left
with a beam of just posetrons. The only
issue is that because of the terrible
efficiency from slowing down those
posetrons, each single shot only
generates around a thousand usable slow
posetrons. But we need millions or even
billions of slow posetrons for the next
stage. So the solution is to accumulate
the posetrons in a particle trap where
over several minutes it builds up a
posetron cloud of around 100 million or
more posetrons which is enough for the
next stage. I said you merge positrons
and antipotons but we do even more
complicated. First we make posetronium.
Posetronum is
>> posetronium.
>> Yes.
>> Posetronium is an electron and a
posetron orbiting each other like a
binary star system. It's an exotic form
of matter and it only lasts about 110th
to 142 nonds before the two come
together and annihilate. The way they
make this is by using strong magnetic
fields to compress the cloud of
posetrons and fire it at porous silicon
dioxide films. When these posetrons
enter these films, they rip away
electrons from their atoms and some of
those electrons then bind with posetrons
to form posetronium. And then a part of
that posetronium diffuses out of the
films into the vacuum of the next stage,
the interaction chamber where it's time
for the final step.
>> So this is what we prepare this here.
>> That's the posetronium.
>> Yes,
>> that's crazy.
>> We send antipotons to the posetronum
where it makes antihydrogen.
>> Now since posetronium only survives for
about 142 nonds, this needs to be timed
perfectly. So, if you want to see where
we we catch the anti-roton.
>> Yes, I would love to see where you catch
the anti-roton. I was not expecting to
get this close.
>> It's right here.
>> Yes.
>> That's awesome. Okay. So, we get the
anti-rotons here.
>> Yes.
>> And then what what what happens?
>> So, it goes there inside this box.
>> Yeah.
>> Inside the box, it will meet the
posetronium.
>> Oh, there meets the posetronium. Kind of
scared, honestly.
It It sounds like there's music in here.
>> As the posetronium enters the
interaction chamber, the anti-roton beam
needs to be fired through at that exact
moment. When done correctly, around 3
million anti-rotons or so pass through
the posetronium. If all goes well,
around one to a few of those anti-rotons
steal a posetron to create an atom of
anti-hydrogen.
Okay, so we've got posetrons coming
through here, all the way through here.
And this is where you capture the
posetron.
>> Yes, we accumulate them.
>> You accumulate them and then you shoot
them through there and you make the
posetronium and then you shoot that into
that chamber. So it mixes with the
anti-roton.
>> Yep.
>> So cool. It's so cool. Right in here is
where they make anti-atoms,
anti-hydrogen. They shoot the
anti-rotons through and they capture
they capture those anti-eleronss to form
anti-hydrogen which then travels through
here and then you know it will go all
the way along there and they do their
experiments. It's absolutely insane. I
feel like I should not be in here but
it's so cool. Now one question I had
after learning all of this is why? I
mean why do this? Because the alpha G
experiment can already make 100
anti-hydrogen atoms in 4 hours using a
much simpler process. So why is the Gar
team spending years to build a particle
accelerator, a posetronium converter,
and a way to shoot the anti-roton
through this posetronium just to make
fewer anti-hydrogen atoms in a slower
and more difficult way. Especially when
you consider that in 2023, Alpha G did
its own test to see whether
anti-hydrogen falls up or down. Well, to
understand why, we need to understand
exactly what it is that Alpha G did.
Their setup works something like this.
Phosetrons are created by a radioactive
source, accumulated, and are then
injected up and trapped. Anti-rotons
then come in from Elena are accumulated
in a trap and then also injected in a
trap that sits just below the posetrons.
Next, the two antiparticle clouds are
gently merged. This causes some of the
anti-rotons to capture a posetron and
form anti-hydrogen.
Now, antihydrogen is neutral, which
means that the penning trap can no
longer hold it. So if nothing else was
done, the anti-hydrogen atoms would
form, drift off, and within micros
seconds annihilate at one of the walls.
It would all be for nothing. And this is
exactly what happened with the earliest
antihydrogen experiments. They couldn't
hold on to it. Fortunately, there is a
way to trap antihydrogen because it has
a small magnetic moment. So a second
magnetic trap was engineered around the
device which could capture the
antihydrogen. Unfortunately, that trap
is pretty weak. So, most anti-hydrogen
atoms escape and annihilate, but a few
stay. And the idea then is simple.
Slowly weaken the magnetic field holding
them. And as the trap gets weaker and
weaker, anti-atoms start to escape. And
if gravity pulls antimatter down, like
normal matter, then more atoms should
escape through the bottom than through
the top. So, what did they find? Does
antimatter fall up or down? They found
that antimatter falls down. So it rules
out any exotic theories of anti-gravity.
They measured the gravitational
acceleration as 75% of normal gravity
plus - 13% plus - 16%. Which is possibly
consistent with normal gravity. But of
course the error bars are huge. And this
is also why GBAR is so important because
their hope is to get the measurement
accuracy down to 1% and ultimately to
one in 100,000.
See, when you're doing a gravity
experiment on atoms like this, you want
those atoms to be as still as possible
before you drop them. In other words,
you want them to be as cold as possible.
Now, alpha G can get really cold to
about 0.5 Kelvin, which is half a degree
above absolute zero. But GBAR wants to
bring this way down to less than 10
micro Kelvin. That is 50,000 times
colder.
The way they plan on doing this is
actually not by making antihydrogen
atoms, but by making an anti-hydrogen
ion, one anti-proton and two posetrons.
The hope is that once an anti-hydrogen
atom has formed, it runs into a second
posetronium atom and steals another
posetron. At first, that might seem
strange because now we're back to having
a charged particle. And as we learned,
you can just drop a charged particle and
measure the effects of gravity, but
charged particles are actually much
easier to trap and cool. And we can use
that because now it can be held in a
much stronger electromagnetic trap. And
once there, you can inject ultra cold
like 10 ml burillium ions that have been
laser cooled. The anti-hydrogen ion then
bounces around and collides with these
burillium ions slowly transferring its
kinetic energy to them and thus cooling
down and they won't annihilate because
both particles are positively charged so
they repel each other. Then you keep
cooling down the burillium ions using
more advanced techniques until you hit
the micro kelvin range and this is
ultimately how they hope to reach a
temperature of around 10 micro kelvin.
Now with the anti-hydrogen ion as still
as possible, they shoot a laser pulse at
it, dislodging one of its posetrons and
resulting in a neutral anti-hydrogen
atom. And as a result, the
electromagnetic trap can no longer hold
it and so it falls around 20 cm. At that
temperature and over that distance, you
can time the fall precisely enough to
measure the gravitational acceleration
to about 1%.
So all of this the particle accelerator
making the posetronium and then the hard
way of cooling it all of it is just to
watch a single anti-atom fall 20 cm
because this process is the only known
way to make anti-hydrogen ions and using
those ions is the only way to get
antimatter cold enough to perform an
accurate enough experiment. Now they
haven't managed to do this yet. So far,
they've only made anti-hydrogen, but if
they can manage, then it would be the
most precise measurement of antimatter
under gravity, although this is likely
still years away.
Now, one thing that makes this research
so tricky and also relatively slow is
that there is only one antimatter
factory in the world. And so, the number
of places that can study real antimatter
is very limited. But that might soon
change. All thanks to another experiment
at the factory. The base experiment was
built to measure the magnetic moment of
the anti-roton. If CPT symmetry holds,
then it should be exactly equal and
opposite to that of the proton. But they
kept running into a problem.
>> Accelerator is continuously ramping
magnetic fields in the background.
>> Right? Even though these fluctuations
were tiny, around 20,000 times weaker
than the Earth's magnetic field, at the
precision Bass was working at, they hit
a wall.
>> The only concept um basically to
overcome this problem is to move the
particles out of the accelerator.
>> So they built a penning trap with its
own power supply, its own cooling
system, and two storage holds for
anti-roton. So now they could fill those
holes with anti-rotons, store them, and
carry them to wherever they wanted. They
just created the world's first portable
antimatter trap.
So of course, I asked them a pressing
scientific question. Are you going to
make it look super futuristic? Because
it it's got to be the most badass
transport container ever made.
>> I just have this um trap here in my
office. Maybe I can show it to you.
>> Oh,
>> this is one of these panning traps and
they are inside the superconducting
magnet. So the the the heavy part is
basically the superconducting magnet.
But these are these trap electrodes and
it works. They have cracked the code of
storing the most volatile substance in
the universe. Their current record for
storing anti-roton is 614 days. That is
they can store antimatter. You know, the
stuff that annihilates as soon as it
touches matter for close to two years.
That is absurd.
>> This is this anti-roton reservoir trap
that stores um antirotons for longer
than 1 or 2 years.
>> That's awesome.
>> But here's what that means. Because if
you can store antimatter for years in a
box and you can put that box on a truck,
then why not ship it? we can start
distributing anti-rotons to ambitious
experiments all around the planet and
everyone who has a good idea what we
could do with these particles will get
these particles. I'm just imagining this
map in my head where you have the big
antimatter factory and then it's going
to be sending antimatter all over the
world to all the top research
institutions.
>> That's great, right? That's a fantastic
vision.
>> Fantastic.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes.
And they've already started. On the 24th
of March 2026, a crane lifted an 800 kg
trap out of the antimatter factory and
loaded it onto a truck which then drove
on a 10 km loop around CERN and it was
filled with 92 anti-rotons.
So perhaps Angels and Demons wasn't that
far off after all. In the near future,
there could be actual boxes of
antimatter that, at least in theory,
could be stolen. So, does that also mean
that they were right about that 1/8 of a
gram of antimatter? Well, we wanted to
find out, so we tested it. I mean, we
simulated it.
>> This is like the most super villain call
I've ever got.
>> I'm really getting into my villain arc
here. Okay, so let's find our poor
target, Fatican City. We've got an
eighth of a gram, you know, selected
right there. 0.125. Who wants to do a
countdown?
>> Three, two, one. Let's go. Let's go.
>> Oh,
>> Okay, so we we've got a few levels of
destruction here. We've got the
fireball. This is just all instantly
vaporized. It's turned into pure plasma,
which is insane.
>> Oh, St. Peter's Basilica. It's got a
temperature of about 100 million degrees
Celsius, which is, you know, pretty
chill. You can see it released about
2.25
* 10 13 jewels, or I guess about 22
trillion jewels, which is the equivalent
of like 36%
of the Hiroshima blast. If we zoom out,
this is the area of third degree burn.
So, your skin gets molten. Bro, you're
having way too much fun with this.
>> Can I ask this question? Like, do we
have a an eighth of a gram of antimatter
available for this? Ask him for a
friend.
>> Can you really steal an eighth of a gram
from CERN?
>> That's a good good question.
>> Do you know how much antimatter you've
made in total in this factory?
>> We make uh in the order of 10 to the 10
uh protons antirotons per year. Now, we
can make an estimate. This facility is
is around since 25 years. So let's say
this is 10 to the 11 protons. A gram
would mean uh 10 to the 23.
So we are talking here of uh well I'm
not very good at man math but it's like
>> a trillionth of a gram.
>> That means that to make 1/8 of a gram of
antimatter the factory would have to run
for longer than the age of the universe.
In fact, if you took all the 10 billion
anti-rotons they make in a year and
annihilated them all at once, you would
produce enough energy to heat 1 milll of
water by about 1° C.
>> I'd love to see Croatia get just for for
size and scale.
>> How much?
>> You tell me.
>> All right. 10 g of antimatter.
>> Sure, let's do it.
>> Oh my god.
So, while 10 g of antimatter would
destroy an entire city,
>> bye-bye hometown.
>> The amounts of antimatter they're making
at CERN are in no way dangerous. Which
is also part of the reason we had some
fun with this simulation because for the
fareseeable future, it's just not
realistic to talk about having
macroscopic amounts of antimatter.
>> Yeah. So, if people want to play around
with this, we'll put a link in the
description. Uh yeah, have fun.
>> Or if you'd rather get some antimatter
yourself without having to rub CERN,
then I'll tell you how to get some. Just
go to your local supermarket and buy
yourself this some bananas.
That's because a banana contains trace
amounts of the radioactive isotope
potassium 40. And roughly every 75
minutes, one of these atoms decays and
releases a posetron. Which means that if
you wanted to match the antimatter
facto's output in terms of
antiparticles, you would need about a
billion bananas.
Now, that's a lot of bananas, and I
don't recommend eating that many. But
the thing is, even if you never eat any
bananas, odds are there are some trace
amounts of radioactive materials inside
of you, and some of those will produce
antimatter. One article estimates that
the average human makes around 180
posetrons per hour. And so there truly
is no need to be scared of antimatter
because you have been your own little
antimatter factory all along.
Hey, just a few final things. The first
thing is I want to give a big shout out
to Physics Girl who made an amazing
video for the antimatter factory years
ago. And ever since I watched that
video, I've always wanted to go. So,
it's been a huge inspiration and I
highly recommend you check out that
video here. The other thing is I want to
give a quick shout out to all the people
at CERN. Those who helped us with all
the animations, those who've hosted us
and taken the time to explain their live
work and everyone else, thank you so
much. And the third and final thank you
is of course, as always, to you. Thank
you so much for watching and I'm excited
to see you at the next one. Anti-Casper.
Casper annihilate.
All right, that's